Guide to the David Ernest Apter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Ernest Apter papers
1920-2002
1951-1960
MS 1806
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
27.5
(23 boxes)
The collection consists of photographs taken by David E. Apter from 1951 to 1960 in the African countries of Ghana (formerly known as the Gold Coast), Nigeria, Rwanda, Uganda, and Benin (formerly known as Dahomey), during the buildup of nationalism and the start of independence. The photographs portray scenes of everyday life in these countries. The collection also includes two photographs of David Apter, taken by Eleanor Apter in 1953 in Achimota, Gold Coast, and by Larissa Leclair in 2002 at Apter's home in North Haven, Connecticut. The uprising in Tiananmen Square in Beijing, China, in 1989, is documented with twenty-nine photographs by Apter. The materials also include photographs documenting Sanrizuka Hantai Dōmei in Japan, 1979-1982; slides of Europe, India and Mexico, 1956-1991; and research materials and correspondence on Africa, 1920-1972.
Apter, David E. (David Ernest), 1924-2010
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Apter, 2002, 2004, and 2010; transferred from Africana Collection Curator, 2014.
Arrangement
Material is arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
David E. Apter was born on December 18, 1924, in New York City. He received his A.B. from Antioch College in 1950 and his M.A. (1952) and Ph.D. (1954) in Political Science from Princeton University. He taught at Northwestern University, the University of Chicago, the University of California at Berkeley and, since 1979, Yale University, where he was the Henry J. Heinz II Professor Emeritus of Comparative Political and Social Development and a senior research scientist in the political science and sociology departments. A former senior fellow of the Whitney Humanities Center, he was executive secretary of the Committee for the Comparative Study of New Nations at the University of Chicago and the director of the Institute of International Studies at Berkeley. At Yale, he was director of the social science division and chair of both the Council of African Studies, and the Department of Sociology. Apter authored numerous books, including Ghana in Transition (originally published as Gold Coast in Transition by Princeton University Press in 1955), The Political Kingdom in Uganda, and Against the State: Politics and Social Protest in Japan, and articles covering a wide range of subjects including comparative politics, political development, and the role of social protest, violence, and revolution in the political process. He spent considerable time studying political movements in Africa, China, Japan, and elsewhere. Apter died on May 4, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The photographs in Accessions 2002-M-089 and 2002-M-090 have been digitally reproduced and are available through the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database. Researchers must use the digitized images rather than the originals.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photographs taken by David E. Apter from 1951 to 1960 in the African countries of Ghana (formerly known as the Gold Coast), Nigeria, Rwanda, Uganda, and Benin (formerly known as Dahomey), during the buildup of nationalism and the start of independence. The photographs portray scenes of everyday life in these countries. The collection also includes two photographs of David Apter, taken by Eleanor Apter in 1953 in Achimota, Gold Coast, and by Larissa Leclair in 2002 at Apter's home in North Haven, Connecticut. The uprising in Tiananmen Square in Beijing, China, in 1989, is documented with twenty-nine photographs by Apter. The materials also include photographs documenting Sanrizuka Hantai Dōmei in Japan, 1979-1982; slides of Europe, India and Mexico, 1956-1991; and research materials and correspondence on Africa, 1920-1972.
General
2002-M-089, box 1, 2002-M-089, box 2: and 2002-M-090, box 1 contained 33 photographic prints that were reported missing in May 2016.
Africa; China -- History -- Tiananmen Square Incident, 1989; Japan; Photographs -- Africa; Photographs -- China; Photographs -- Japan; Apter, David E. (David Ernest), 1924-2010
- Original Accession, Accession 2002-M-089
  Conditions Governing Access
  The photographs in Accessions 2002-M-089 have been digitally reproduced and are available through the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database. Researchers must use the digitized images rather than the originals.
  General
  Prints located in box 2 reported missing in May 2016.
  - Photographs used in "Africa Photographs, 1952-1960" an exhibit staged in the Memorabilia Room, Sterling Memorial Library, Yale University, February 4 - March 8, 2002, 1951-1960 (Box 1)
    Prints contained in this box were reported missing in May 2016.
  - Photographs used in "Africa Photographs, 1952-1960" an exhibit staged in the Memorabilia Room, Sterling Memorial Library, Yale University, February 4 - March 8, 2002, 1951-1960 (Box 2)
    Prints located in this box were reported missing in May 2016.
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-090
  The photographs in Accessions 2002-M-090 have been digitally reproduced and are available through the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database. Researchers must use the digitized images rather than the originals.
  Prints located in box 1 reported missing in May 2016
  - Photographs, 1951-1960, 2002 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-030
  - Photographs from Tiananmen Square, Beijing, China, 1989 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1920-1991; Accession 2010-M-072
  - Papers, 1920-1972
    - Africa, general, 1955-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Democratic Republic of the Congo, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ghana
      - Material from the Busia period, 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      - 1920, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Senegal, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Tanganyika and Uganda, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Uganda, 1945-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Photographs, 1952-1982
    - Sanrizuka Hantai Dōmei (Sanrizuka Opposition Alliance) images published in Against the State, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Africa original series, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
    - Japan, Circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
      Scope and Contents
      Some images are 11x14" duplicates of Sanrizuka Hantai Dōmei photographs.
  - Slides, 1956-1991
    Items have been removed from binders; original order was maintained.
    - Greece and Dubrovnik, 1965, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Italy, 1964-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Tasmania and Hobart, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - India: Malabari Coast, Cochin and environs, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Holland, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Buchwald, East Germany, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Israel, 1974, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Copenhagen, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Berlin before the Wall, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Prague, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - East Germany behind the Wall, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Jena and Dresden, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Austria, including Baden, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Slovakia, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Poland May Day Parade, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bielefeld, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Russia, including Moscow, 1979, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Madrid, Spain, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Mexico, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Additional Material, Circa 1965-1989; Accession 2012-M-061
  The 2012-M-061 addition includes photographs from the Middle East, 1978; Peru and Bolivia, 1965; China, 1986-1989; and Japan, 1977-1981; as well as Wallingford and New Haven, Connecticut.
  - Photographs
    - Africa, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - China, Circa 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - China or Japan, Circa 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Connecticut, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Photographs include images of the neighborhood of Fair Haven Heights and the Quinnipiac river.
    - Connecticut, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Egypt, Circa 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Iran, Circa 1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Israel, Circa 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Japan, Circa 1977-1981 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Japan, Circa 1977-1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - South America, Circa 1965 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
    - South America, Circa 1965 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - Slides
    - China, Circa 1986-1989 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - China and Japan, Circa 1977-1989 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Iran and Egypt, Circa 1978 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Israel, Syria, and Damascus, Circa 1978 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 1950-1969, 2011; Accession 2014-M-051; 1.5; (3 boxes)
  - Afrique Oriental Francaise (AOF) constitutions, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Apter, David
    - Correspondence, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Interview with Kofi Busia, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Manuscripts and Archives (MSSA) ceremony bringing his African photographs to the African collections, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Speaking engagements, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Writings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The United Nations and the Peace Corps, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carew, Jan, "The Coup in Ghana", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Carnegie project on political developments in West Africa, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Congo crisis, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - French West Africa documents, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - French West Africa and Nigeria, political parties, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Forum Service: Congress for Cultural Freedom, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ghana
    - Documents on Gold Coast independence, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Convention People's Party (C.P.P.), 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Nkrumah and the creation of a one-party state, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Peace Corps, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Young Pioneers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kenya
    - Miscellaneous documents, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Press Office handouts, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - List of Soviet Africanists, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mulumba, Semakule, Manuscripts on the removal of the Kabaka, including the Kabaka's map of Uganda, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nigeria
    - Action Group Congress Party, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Documents on preparations for independence, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Interviews in Ilorin, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - National Convention of Nigerian Citizens, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Nigerian National Democratic Party, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Nigerian People's Party, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Nigerian Youth Congress, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Northern People's Congress, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Research for Development in West Africa. Nigeria, Ibadan., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rhodesia, Independence documents, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Senegal
    - Interterritorial Parties, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Parti Africain de l'Independance (PAI), 1950s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Parti du Regroupement Africain (PAR), 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Union Progressiste Senegalaise (UPS), 1960s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Responsibility of a Major University" (speech), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Signatories to the Organization of African Unity Charter, 1963 May 25 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Tanganyika, Study of African Leadership (Tanzania), 1960s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - United States Department of State, Press releases concerning Africa, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - United States Senate Task Force on Africa, recommendations, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Williams, G. Mennen, Addresses on Africa, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)